<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the last generall asise holden for the county of Sommerset at Taunton. By William Sclater Batchelar in Diuinitie, and minister of the word of God at Pitmsiter</title>
            <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11602</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21843</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100966</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836793</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836793</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1080</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11602)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1080)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1187:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the last generall asise holden for the county of Sommerset at Taunton. By William Sclater Batchelar in Diuinitie, and minister of the word of God at Pitmsiter</title>
                  <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Griffin for Henry Fetherstone, dwelling in Pauls church-yard at the signe of the Rose,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's device (McKerrow 293) on title page.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1080:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1080:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT the laſt generall Aſsiſe holden <hi>for the County of</hi> SOMMERSET at TAVNTON.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Sclater</hi> Batchelar in <hi>Diuinitie, and Miniſter of the Word of</hi> God at PITMISTER.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Edward Griffin</hi> for <hi>Henry Fetherſtone,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard at the ſigne of the Roſe. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1080:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1080:2"/>
            <head>To THE WORSHIPFVLL M. IOHN COLLES Eſquire, <hi>High Sheriffe of</hi> Sommerſet, <hi>Mercy</hi> and peace be multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>JR, J here tender to your view my Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at your instance, heard with your beſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, preſſed to the Preſſe by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of friends: occaſioned by thoſe many abbreuiations, whereto the iniunction of breuitie from ſuperiours forced me. The ſumme of the whole is this: Therein ſee you your ſtation in the Common-wealth warranted by Gods ordinance: the rich Grace of
<pb facs="tcp:1080:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> God in your aduancement to ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent dignitie: withall, the dutie the Lord expects from you in reſpect of your aduancement. To preuent pride, you are remembred of humane frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: to procure vprightneſſe in procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings iudiciall, the terrours of the Lords iudgement are offered to your meditation. Vſe it as your direction to theſe ends: and thus thinke of the Author, <hi>he had rather be deemed any thing then vnthankfull.</hi> So with my prayers to God for continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and multiplication of all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly and earthly bleſsings vpon you, J reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your thankfull and obſeruant welwiller, WILLIAM SCLATER.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Pitmiſter,
<date>Iuly <hi>25. 1616.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1080:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT <hi>the laſt Generall Aſsiſe holden</hi> for the County of <hi>Sommerſet</hi> at TAVNTON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 82.6.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> I haue ſaid ye are Gods, and ye all are ſonnes of the moſt high.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> But ye ſhall die like men, and fall like one of the Princes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Prophet, whether <hi>Aſaph</hi> or <hi>Dauid,</hi> hauing taxed the iniuſtice of the Iudges of that time, and addreſſing himſelfe to denounce Gods iudgement againſt them, in theſe words ſeemes to preoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupate the ſecure thoughts of their pride. Gods they were by office on earth, without controll therefore of men; and, as they ſeemed to conceit, exempted from cenſure of God himſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:1080:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The anſwer is in the perſon of God: 1. by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, Its true, <hi>I haue ſaid ye are Gods:</hi> 2. by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, <hi>but ye ſhall die as men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words are two things obſeruable: 1. the dignitie of the Magiſtrates office; 2. the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of their perſons: their dignitie amplified, 1. by the author, God, <hi>I haue ſaid;</hi> 2. by the eminence, <hi>ye are Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their infirmitie noticed in their death, in their fall; both amplified by ſimilitude or paritie; <hi>yee ſhall die like men, and fall like one of the Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt of the author: <hi>I haue ſaid.</hi> This <hi>dixi</hi> of the Lord for Magiſtrates office, ſounds aloud in Scripture, in nature, in heauen, hell, the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, mans nature and conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 8.</note>
               <hi>By me Kings raigne,</hi> ſaith Gods eſſentiall wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: he meanes not only by the ſecret diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his prouidence, but by expreſſe warrant of his ordinance. The Apoſtle in new Teſtament (to preuent the idle exceptions of Anabaptiſts)<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>There is no power but of God:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Aug. contra Fauſt. Manich. lib. <hi>22.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Siue iubente, ſiue ſinente,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> by Gods either commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or permiſſion: thats <hi>Auguſtines</hi> gloſſe: the text addes more: <hi>The powers that are, are</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and ordained of God.<note n="*" place="margin">Theophylact. in Rom. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> The perſons are ſometimes intruders, as in caſe of vſurpation; ſometimes abuſers of their authoritie, as when they tyrannize: but the powers themſelues haue God for their author.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>S. Peter</hi> indeed cals them<note n="c" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>humane ordinances;</hi> but hee ſpeakes of the ſeuerall formes, not of the ſubſtance of gouernment.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:1080:4"/>
            <p>In nature it ſelfe are found impreſſions of this ordinance: in heauen amongſt Angels are<note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and thrones.</hi> And there is an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Michael the</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Iude 9.</note> 
               <hi>Archangell.</hi> Amongſt the Spheres, there is one firſt moueable commander of all the inferiours with his motion. Amongſt Starres, there are greater and leſſer lights, rulers amongſt the reſt. Yea ſuch a power there is of this <hi>dixi,</hi> that the ſound thereof hath pierced downe to hell. Deuils haue their principalities, not onely ouer other creatures, but reſpectiuely amongſt themſelues: therefore it is ſaid,<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 25.41.</note> 
               <hi>the Deuill and his Angels,</hi> and<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 12.24</note> 
               <hi>Beelzebub the Prince of Deuils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſay nothing of bruit creatures, amongſt which yet Philoſophers haue obſerued a perfect forme of regiment and policie: in man that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, how doth euery thing pleade for gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? his conſtitution, his inclination, his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. So hath God tempered him in his fabricke and conſtitution, that we ſhall ſee in euery part of his nature ſomething that rules, ſomething made to be ruled. In the compoſition of his body there is an element predominant; the ſoule hath ouer the body <hi>Imperium</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; the minde ouer the affectuous part <hi>Imperium politicum.</hi> If nothing elſe euince it, that awfull ſubmiſſion to regiment, which conſcience ſuggeſts to ſauages, ſufficiently proues it. As farre as that principle is heard of, that there is a <hi>Rex Regum,</hi> and <hi>Dominus Dominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium;</hi> where euer its knowne that <hi>there is a God that iudgeth the earth,</hi> its knowne alſo and receiued, that there are nominall Gods on earth, with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1080:5"/> next to the ſupreme Maieſtie to be adored. Amongſt the barbarous Nations of late diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, hath beene found, as ſome religion and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, ſo ſome forme of policie and ciuill gouernment. Let it bee true that <hi>Tully</hi> hath in commendation of his Oratorie, that it firſt drew into ciuill communion the diſperſed and bruitiſh companies of men: yeeld that that others haue, that fiction of diuine viſions procured authoritie to lawes: let theſe be meanes; ſome principle there muſt be acknowledged in mans nature, fit to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge equitie of ſuch conſtitutions.<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſt politic. lib <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> ſaith there is in euery man <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an affectuous and no leſſe then impetuous inclination to ſuch ſocietie. And if any be vnfitted for that ſtate, he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a bruit; if any need it not, he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, God. But ouer and aboue all this, it more then ſeemes that naturall conſcience, amongſt other common notions, hath receiued the impreſſion of this principle: how elſe comes it, that (a few extraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant natures only excepted) ſuch awfull ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is found in all, to men of our owne mould? yet in our apprehenſion clad with ſuch venerable ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, that the culpable ſcarce behold them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trembling; and the guiltleſſe yeeld willing reuerence to their perſons. So euery way hath God pleaſed to make knowne his ordinance for magiſtracie.</p>
            <p>It were wonder ſuch a principle ſhould finde oppoſition in the nature of man, by nature the moſt ſociable of all ſenſible creatures: more ſtrange, that amongſt Chriſtians (as they would
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1080:5"/> be eſteemed) this conſtitution ſhould be thought either Heatheniſh, or Iewiſh. In a word, two ſorts of men we finde oppoſite to this ordinance: Firſt are they that out of a vicious diſpoſition of their hearts, deſire to liue as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith they are<note n="h" place="margin">Iob 11.12.</note> borne, <hi>like the wilde Aſſe-colt in the wilderneſſe:</hi> and for none other thing diſlike gouernment, ſaue onely that it reſtraines their vnbridled corruption. That bruitiſh ſtrumpet in the Poet quarrels at Gods prouidence, that hauing ſet no bounds to the luſt of beaſts, hath taught men to reuerence the bond of bloud. A generation fitter to be confuted with a clubbe then with an argument. There once was ſuch a ſtate of Gods people the Iewes, liuing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controll of authoritie: ſee to what extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties corruption breakes forth, notwithſtanding all the reuelations of Gods will from heauen, and the freſh memorie of his vengeance vpon the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites:</hi> the groſſeſt Idolatrie, and moſt vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall luſt they are carried beadlong into. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is noted:<note n="i" place="margin">Iudg. 17 5.6. Iudg. 18.1.30. Iudg. 19.1.22.</note> 
               <hi>In thoſe dayes there was no King in Iſrael, but euery man did what ſeemed right in his owne eyes.</hi> And it was a prudent obſeruation of that States-man in the remiſneſſe of <hi>Nerua</hi> his raigne: <hi>Its better to liue where nothing, then where all things are lawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort is of them that vnder pretence of I know not what Chriſtian perfection, haue aboliſhed Magiſtracie amongſt other Iewiſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, and limit all precepts of ſubiection gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in new Teſtament, to Magiſtrates heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. Let vs ſee a little whether the ordinance
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1080:6"/> were in likelihood temporarie. Firſt, we know no tranſient ceremonie that had place in mans inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie; and haue reaſon to teach, that euen in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie there was a ſubordination of one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though without paine as now it is. That reaſon of the Apoſtle, <hi>Man was</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>firſt formed, of him and after him the woman,</hi> had place in ſtate of innocencie.</p>
            <p>Beſides, we hold it a rule, what euer ordinance knits man to God, man to man, is of perpetuall vſe to the Church of God: and ſo much onely of Iewiſh ordinances we thinke aboliſhed, as aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted man from God, or man from man. Therefore of difference of meats, wee ſay it was temporarie, it was part of the<note n="l" place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>partition wall</hi> betwixt Iew and Gentile: therefore of rigour and iuſtification of the law morall, its alſo abrogated, becauſe it main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſeparation betwixt God and man. So wee tremble to thinke of Magiſtracie.</p>
            <p>To bee ſhort, if the ordinance were Iewiſh, what's the reaſon <hi>Paul</hi> reckoning vp the gifts of God for right ordering of the Church of new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, amongſt others mentions<note n="m" place="margin">1. Cor 12.28.</note> 
               <hi>gouernments,</hi> that is, gifts of gouernment? Queſtionleſſe hee ſaw, that euen in ſtate of greateſt perfection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians, there were that ſhould neede reſtraint by gouernment; and whoſe beſt ſafetie ſhould ſtand in this, that they were aſſigned to the regiment of others. Let vs ſee whether in like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood the authoritie be limited to Magiſtrates heatheniſh. The title of Magiſtrates is, to be<note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God;</hi> their end and vſe, the good of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1080:6"/> Church. According to this gloſſe of Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, the honourableſt place of ſeruice to God is appropriated to Ethnickes, and therein Chriſtians without intruſion cannot meddle. Their end, the good of Gods Church, which who can but abſurdly imagine, ſhould flow more kindly from heatheniſh, then from Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauls</hi> counſell is to<note n="o" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.1.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>pray for Kings, and thoſe in authoritie,</hi> that they may be conuerted; withall hee intimates the good iſſues flowing from their conuerſion, <hi>peace, honeſtie, godlineſſe,</hi> to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God. It were ſtrange that from Princes heatheniſh we ſhould expect furtherance in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and honeſtie, and not rather from them conuerted to Chriſtianitie: nay, why pray wee for their conuerſion, if from their Ethniciſme ſuch gracious furtherances may be expected?</p>
            <p>Its promiſed as a bleſſing to the Church of new Teſtament, that ſhee ſhould haue<note n="p" place="margin">Iſa. 49.23.</note> 
               <hi>Kings her nurſing Fathers, and Queenes her nurſing Mothers.</hi> Neuer ſaw the Church Chriſtian this promiſe accompliſhed, till the happy conuerſion of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> to Chriſtianitie; except to ſucke the bloud of the Church, were to be nurſes to the Church, ſuch fauour neuer taſted ſhee from heathens. It remaines then, that notwithſtanding thoſe cauil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome exceptions of licentious Anabaptiſts, magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie hath Gods ordinance to commend it to the perpetuall vſe of the Church to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>This comfort ariſeth to Magiſtrates from this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1080:7"/> meditation; that they know their ſtanding war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by Gods ordinance.</p>
            <p>Thus of the author of their authoritie: let vs conſider their eminence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye are Gods.]</hi> The impertinencies of <hi>Hierome</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in their Commentaries, extending the dignitie to all Chriſtians, the circumſtances of the text apparantly diſcouer. To Magiſtrates, not to all Gods children, its ſaid, <hi>yee are Gods:</hi> Gods, 1. by analogie: 2. Gods by deputation: 3. Gods by participation. The expoſitions haue ſome ſhew of difference, but are all coordinate. The analogie ſtands in ſemblance of actions and imployments to thoſe of the great God of heauen and earth. As hee hath his ſeat for iudgement, ſo theſe their Tribunals and iudiciall Thrones, wherein to iudge of the actions of men:<note n="*" place="margin">Theodoret. in Pſal. <hi>81.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>tanquam in hoc Deum imitantes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Theodoret. There is</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Iac. 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>one Law-giuer,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Iames;</hi> hee meanes <hi>primarius.</hi> And yet of Princes, ſaith the wiſdome of God;<note n="r" place="margin">Pro. 8.15.</note> 
               <hi>By me</hi> (that is, by my allowance and inſpiration) <hi>Princes decree iuſt things.</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 12.19.</note> 
               <hi>Vengeance is Gods, he will repay it;</hi> yet Magiſtrates are<note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>Miniſters of God to execute vengeance on thoſe that doe euill.</hi> I am loth to make them tranſcendents; yet ſuch ſure is their authoritie on earth <hi>ſupra ſeriem:</hi> without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll of any, ſaue of that <hi>Rex Regum.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Tertullian. ad Sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>m.</note> 
               <hi>Colimus Imperatorem</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tertullian) vt hominem à Deo ſecundum, &amp; quicquid eſt, à Deo conſecutum, ſolo Deo minorem.</hi> We reuerence the Emperour as a man next vnto God, and as one that hath what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he hath from God; inferiour to God only.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1080:7"/> 
               <hi>It behoueth thee,</hi> ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">Agapet. in parae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian. Imp.</note> 
               <hi>Agapetus</hi> to the Emperor of his time, <hi>to charge vpon thy ſelfe a neceſsity of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Lawes, as hauing none on earth that can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell thee.</hi> So ſtand the Analogy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gods by deputation,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">2. Par. 19 8</note> 
               <hi>yee iudge not for men, but for the Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iehoſhaphat, the</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Deut. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>iudgements is Gods</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes.</hi> Magiſtrates are his mouthes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, his hands to execute it. Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are Gods vicegerents on earth, by whom as by ſecond cauſes he gouerns the world. Therefore <hi>Samuel</hi> being contemned in his authoritie, when he puts vp his complaint to God, receiues this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, <hi>The people had not reiected him,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">1. Sam 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>but God Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius ſcil. vices gerebat,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aquinas, de regimine principum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gods by participation;<note n="*" place="margin">Auguſtin. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> tractat. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Participando fiunt Dij</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine, tanquam luminaillum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>inata.</hi> As ſtarres participate their light from the ſunne, the <hi>primum lucidum;</hi> ſo theſe their authoritie from the ſupreame maieſty. The glorious maieſty of God hath pleaſed to caſt on them, ſome beames of his own excellency, to make them venerable in the eyes and hearts of men. Yee haue heard your dignitie; I beſeech you take notice of your duty.</p>
            <p>Its true I confeſſe, this eminence of dignity is originally in the ſupreame Magiſtrate, yet is there a ſtreame thereof deriued to his delegates, which yee are. Thus thinke, the higher the Lord hath aduanced you, the more he expects to be honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red of you. The rule is <hi>Leuit.</hi> 10.3. <hi>God will bee ſanctified in thoſe that come neere him;</hi> either by a more then ordinary meaſure of holineſſe in their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1080:8"/> liues, or by his extraordinary vengeance. Ye vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly miſtake the matter, if becauſe yee haue the moderation of humane Lawes, yee thinke your ſelues exempt from ſtricteſt obſeruance of the Lawes of God. Kings themſelues haue charge,<note n="z" place="margin">Deut. 17.19</note> 
               <hi>to read in the Law and to feare that God</hi> that hath ſo highly aduanced them. And ſure it is, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we thinke; ſinnes take their greatneſſe in part from the greatneſſe of the perſons by whom they are committed. The ſheckle of the Sanctuary, was double in weight to the common ſheckle; to peize aſwell the ſinnes of the Prieſts, as the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of the people. The expiatorie ſacrifice, for the ſinne of the Prieſt,<note place="margin">Leuit. 4.</note> was as great as that for the whole congregation. The reaſon I thinke is all one for the Magiſtrate. Gods mercy as great to him in his aduancement; his ſin in the iſſues as pernicious.</p>
            <p>If that preuaile not, weigh well how euery way quarrel-ſome at the liues of Magiſtrates the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are.<note n="*" place="margin">Plutarch in precept Reipub. gerend.</note> 
               <hi>Cimon</hi> at Athens was taxed for this, that ſometimes he dranke wine. Romanes, that could finde no other fault in <hi>Scipio,</hi> made his ſleepe a matter of imputation. In <hi>Pompei</hi> the great it was made matter of criminous obſeruation, that hee ſcratched his head with one finger. And general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you ſhall finde it true that <hi>Plutarch</hi> obſerued; As the leaſt blemiſh in the face, be it but a wart, is more conſpicuous and troubleſome, then were deformed ſcarres in the reſt of the bodie; ſo the moates of rulers liues, ſeeme beames in the eyes of the people.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:1080:8"/>
            <p>Conſider alſo how preualent your examples are, either in good or euill: if good, none ſo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall or wholſome; if ill, none ſo pernicious for imitation. Saith <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Peter, Why</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>conſtraineſt thou the Gentiles</hi> to bee circumciſed? what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſory worke had <hi>Peter</hi> ouer Gentiles? how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraines he them to circumciſion? his gifts, and gracious carriage, had wonne him eſteeme in the Church of God, and his example ſeemed a Law; therefore ſaid <hi>Ierome</hi> truely; <hi>Coegit non verbo ſed exemplo.</hi> As in ſayling, ſaith <hi>Agapetus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Agape. qua ſupra.</note> the error of an ordinary ſhip-man brings little detriment to the burthen, but the miſtake of the Steres-man, or Pilot hazards the whole voyage: So in the Common-wealth, the ſinnes of the <hi>vulgus</hi> doe little harme by infection; but the euil example of eminent Rulers, are no leſſe then peſtilent and banefull. Now bleſſed be God that hath inclined your hearts, to more then wonted conſcience of the Sabaoth; my hope is, former neglects haue beene lamented. Gods people, I dare ſay, bleſſe his name for the amendment. But this I aſſure you, howſoeuer the oddes be great betwixt the important affaires of a Kingdome, and the baſe pleaſures of the multitude; yet more preuailed the example of you mortall gods to incourage to prophaneneſſe then the example of the great God of heauen and earth, propounded<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 20.11</note> in the <hi>precept,</hi> to perſwade the ſanctifying of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth.</p>
            <p>If none of theſe moue, weigh well, how accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to rules of Scripture, the ſinnes of others,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1080:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> committed by any our occaſion, become ours by iuſt imputation. <hi>What euill is this that</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Nehe. 13.17</note> 
               <hi>yee doe in breaking the Lords Sabaoth?</hi> ſaid <hi>Nehemiah</hi> to the Rulers of Ieruſalem; that ſinned, not by perſonall commiſſion, but by partiall conniuence, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of the ſinnes of others. Now, God bee mercifull to the ſinnes of our perſons. <hi>If thou ſhalt be extreame to marke</hi> what in our owne liues <hi>wee doe amiſse,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 130.3</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall be able to abide it?</hi> To theſe, if the burthen of other mens ſinnes be added, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by any our occaſion, how can our ſoules but ſinke vnder the weight to the bottome of the nethermoſt hell?</p>
            <p>Pardon my length in this admonition: the hearts and liues of your Lordſhips are to mee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 135.</note> 
               <hi>charitie bindes</hi> me <hi>to thinke the beſt;</hi> and I haue learned of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.20</note> 
               <hi>not to blaſpheme emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Rulers, no not in my ſecret thought.</hi> Your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome I preſume hath learn'd to interpret admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, not alwaies as imputations, but when we are guiltleſſe, as preuentions.</p>
            <p>But ſhall I tell you what is obſerued in our pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty gods? our <hi>Dij minorum gentium: Mentior,</hi> if their liues proclaime not, that they thinke autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie an immunitie from obedience to the Lawes of God: and ſo liue, as if they fancied no other happineſſe in their dignities, then that they bring with them licenſe to ſinne without controll of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. <hi>Tully</hi> tells of one,<note n="*" place="margin">Auguſtin. de ciuit. Dei lib. <hi>5.</hi> ap <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Qui peccandi licentiâ foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix appellabatur,</hi> had gotten him <hi>Foelix</hi> almoſt for his ſurname, becauſe hee was a licentiate in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>O miſerum,</hi> ſaid <hi>Auguſtine, cui peccare lice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:1080:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> Wretched man that had licenſe to ſinne. Let that happineſſe betide that perſon with whom God is angry for euer.</p>
            <p>And generally yee ſhall obſerue, euen ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſinnes proue diminutiues when they fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to great perſons. As the audacious<note n="*" place="margin">Auguſtin. de C uitat. Dei lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Pirate chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged by <hi>Alexander</hi> for infeſting the ſea, made anſwere freely; <hi>Becauſe I doe it in a Fly-boat I am called a Pirate; becauſe thou in a great Nauy, thou art called an Emperour.</hi> That which we ſilly men call the language of hell, profane daliance with Gods name in common ſwearing, amongſt our gal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lants hath the eſteeme of Retorique; and oathes they reckon amongſt the ornaments and flowers of ſpeech; they ſerue to fill vp the <hi>hiatus</hi> of their broken ſentences. Voluptuous lyuing, to eat, drink, ſleepe, and riſe vp to play, wee in our ſimplicitie terme the life of a beaſt. That <hi>bonum pecudum,</hi> great ones count their felicity, and haue cloſed it now in their definition; what is a Gentle-man but his pleaſure?<note n="*" place="margin">Cicer Tuſcu. quaeſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vox pecudis non hominis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tully</hi> truly, As if they were made in the earth, as <hi>Leuiathan</hi> in the ſea, for nothing but to take their paſtime therein. What ſhould I ſpeake of that gluttonous bouzing, taken vp in great houſes, as part of their deuotion? as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> notes the beaſtly cuſtome in his time.<note n="*" place="margin">Ambroſe de He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bibamus pro ſalute imperatorum, &amp; qui non biberit, ſit reus in deuotione.</hi> Let vs drinke to the health of the King, who ſo pledgeth not his health, let him bee culpable in point of deuotion. O obſequie of pious deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> ironically, or rather ô
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1080:10"/> fooliſhneſſe of men, that thinke drunkenneſſe a ſacrifice to God; as if the God wee ſerue were as <hi>Bacchus</hi> the Idoll of the heathen, to be propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with intemperance.<note n="g" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Oremus pro ſalute Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum,</hi> pray for the health and ſaluation of Kings, that's <hi>Pauls</hi> deuotion. If ſuch be your liues, this your obſeruance of that God that hath ſo highly aduanced you, take heed it proue not your porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at the laſt, that the wiſe man hath; <hi>Potentes po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentèr tormenta patientur,</hi> mighty men ſhall bee mightily tormented.</p>
            <p>One thing more let mee adde on this ground, as more neerely concerning your Lordſhips: Analogie you haue in dignitie to the great God of heauen and earth: I beſeech you be carefull in your executions to maintaine the proportion. <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſhaphat</hi> hath particularized it in his charge to the Iudges of his time, vpon this ground, either of analogie, or deputation:<note n="h" place="margin">2 Chron. 197.</note> 
               <hi>Ye iudge not for men, but for the Lord, therefore let the feare of the Lord bee vpon you; take heed and doe it, for there is no iniquitie with the Lord, nor reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts.</hi> The charge runs often for impartialitie in iudgement: ye ſhall iudge the ſmall as well as the great, and haue no reſpect of perſons in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; not feare the face of the mighty, nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme a poore man in his cauſe: not fauour the perſon of the poore, nor honour the perſon of the mighty. Know it for ſuretie, iniquitie dwels not all in cottages, but findes entertainment in ſieled houſes. I would they were not, ſome of them, as its ſaid of <hi>Shinar,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Zech 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>the land where wickedneſſe is ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1080:10"/> as vpon her owne baſe. Ieremy</hi> in the ſearch hee made in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> for a man, found goodneſſe as rare among<note n="k" place="margin">Ier. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>the great ones,</hi> as amongſt the <hi>vulgus.</hi> The ſtate of our time and Kingdome is not much vnlike. My counſell is this onely: Let neuer ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uillers haue cauſe to ſay of our lawes, as <hi>Anachar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> ſpake tartly of thoſe of <hi>Scythia,</hi> they are as ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders webs, the great flies breake thorow, the ſmaller onely are holden.</p>
            <p>For gifts, how profeſſeth the great Iudge, that herein requires your imitation, a holy ſcorne of them?<note n="l" place="margin">Mic. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>Thouſands of Rammes, and ten thouſand riuers of oile,</hi> none of theſe ſo precious in his eyes, as is the preſeruation of iuſtice. Let the ſame minde be in you. What <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> ſay you to corrupting bribers;<note n="m" place="margin">Act. 8.20.</note> 
               <hi>Thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney periſh with thee,</hi> that thinkeſt ſo ſacred a thing as iuſtice, may be peruerted by money. Withall forget not what <hi>Auguſtine</hi> admoniſheth, that there is ſomething equiualent to a bribe, as much tainting the ſoule with guilt of iniuſtice, whether it be done <hi>prece</hi> or <hi>pretio, timore</hi> or <hi>amore,</hi> the ſinne is the ſame. <hi>Pilate</hi> perhaps could waſh his hands of bribes, not therefore of Chriſts bloud. The feare or fauour of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſuggeſted by the people, (<note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 19.12.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art not Caeſars friend</hi>) was equiualent to a bribe, and ſwaied him againſt iuſtice to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne an innocent. The<note n="o" place="margin">1. Reg. 21.9.10.11.12.13.14.</note> Iudges of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that ſentenced <hi>Naboth</hi> to death, wee reade not to haue beene corrupted with bribes; but there was ſomething equiualent, for which their ſoules to this day frie in hell, except they repented; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1080:11"/> it was feare of <hi>Ieſabels</hi> violence, or hope of fauour and preferment by her, that procured their cruell obſequiouſneſſe to her bloudy man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date. My Lords, hee that ſaid <hi>yee are Gods,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires you in iudgement to put off all partiall hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane affections, and to frame your proceedings to thoſe of the great Iudge of heauen and earth: ſo doing, his promiſe is <hi>to be</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">2 Chro. 19.6.</note> 
               <hi>with you in the cauſe and iudgement.</hi> Giue leaue now a little to direct my ſpeech to thoſe of inferiour ranke imploied in this ſeruice: they haue alſo their meditations na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally affoorded from conſideration of your dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. Conſider it ſeriouſly, beloued Chriſtians, you that haue to deale, whether by way of infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, or teſtimonie, or howſoeuer. They are Gods by office and deputation, before whom ye ſtand; and the great God of heauen and earth<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 82 1.</note> 
               <hi>proteſteth his preſence in the aſſembly of his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents.</hi> Know for a ſuretie, yee haue God a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator, a witneſſe, a Iudge of all your proceedings. The obligation of an oath is ſacred, wherein you<note n="r" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>conteſt the diuine Maieſtie, and engage your ſoules to his wrath,</hi> in caſe you deale falſly or fraudulently before his Deputies. Let the feare of the Lord be vpon you. Tremble to play with the name of God in an oath before his Vice-gerents. The ſinnes of the Country you cannot be ignorant of, they are growne <hi>clamantia,</hi> and the ſinners of no leſſe then Sodomiticall impudencie:<note n="ſ" place="margin">Iſa. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>They declare their ſinnes like Zodom, and hide them not.</hi> The mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of <hi>Pauls</hi> times is long ſince worne out of vſe. It was wont to be ſaid,<note n="t" place="margin">1. Theſſ 5 7.</note> 
               <hi>They that are drunken, are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1080:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> drunken in the night:</hi> and the ſpeech was once pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbiall, <hi>He that euill doth,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Ioh. 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>hates the light.</hi> Deeds of darkneſſe are now done at noone-day; and gluttonie is now no longer matter of<note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 13.13.</note> 
               <hi>chambering,</hi> the very ſtreets are filled with filthy vomitings.</p>
            <p>I could wiſh it were matter of inquirie by your Law, the horrible dalliance with Gods name in vaine ſwearing; and can but wonder, how in a Chriſtian Kingdome, a ſinne of ſo great impietie hath ſo long wanted reſtraint by penall lawes. The names of Princes wee are iuſtly tender of, and the reproachfull traducing of their perſons is in ſome caſes capitall. For my part I could wiſh <hi>Moſes</hi> Law reuiued, <hi>Who ſo blaſphemes the Ruler of the people, ſhall be put to death:</hi> but withall cannot but lament, that the dreadfull name of the Lord of hoſts ſhould be ſo freely permitted to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane abuſe of euery godleſſe miſcreant; and ſhall neuer thinke the Kingdome ſecured from Gods wrath, till ſuch time as wee haue learned to<note n="y" place="margin">Eccl. 9.2.</note> 
               <hi>feare an oath. Becauſe of oathes</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Ier. 23.10.</note> 
               <hi>the Land mournes.</hi> And queſtionleſſe that damned crue of mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie periuers iſſueth out of this damnable crue of common ſwearers. Through too much familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie with oathes, Gods name is growne into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; and whileſt men make no conſcience of ſwearing vainly, they grow at length to make as little of ſwearing falſly.</p>
            <p>That of Recuſancie I know is commonly mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of inquiſition; and yet to this day, the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſorts of Recuſants are either vnknowne, or winked at. There are beſides our ſuperſtitious
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1080:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> Recuſants the Papiſts, and the curious Recuſants, the brethren (as they would be called) of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brotherly ſeparation, a ſort of prophane, I know not whether I may ſay Recuſants or Negligents: men that our of a godleſſe diſpoſition, in very contempt of all Religion,<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 10.25.</note> 
               <hi>forſake our aſſemblies.</hi> The liuing God is ſcarce ſerued with ſuch deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his Temple on the dayes of aſſembling, as <hi>Bacchus</hi> the Idoll of the heathen by theſe men vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Ale-bench. I beſeech you that haue to deale by way of information, of all others let not theſe profane perſons be forgotten. We wonder much without any cauſe of wonder, at the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of Recuſants. Know this for a rule, <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie hath a naturall iſſue out of prophaneneſſe.</hi> And wee haue no reaſon to maruell that men ſhould fall from atheiſme to ſuperſtition, from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe vnto Poperie. Its Gods iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on them <hi>that haue not</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Theſſ. 2.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>receiued the loue of the truth, to ſend vpon them ſtrong deluſions to beleeue lies, that they all might be damned that beleeued not the truth, but had pleaſure in vnrighteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, (that no ſort of men may lacke their portion) are they Gods Vice-gerents that are au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized to iudgement? Mee thinkes then they ſhould tremble that haue to deale by way of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation or pleading, to giue patronage to an euill cauſe. How true it is I ſay not; but its <hi>vox populi,</hi> that Lawyers in their couetouſneſſe are of <hi>Abſoloms</hi> minde in his ambition;<note n="c" place="margin">2 Sam. 15.3</note> 
               <hi>Euery mans cauſe is good, it lackes but indifferent audience.</hi> Its an ill cauſe, they ſay, that admits no colour, that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1080:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> findes no aduocate; a rough ſtone ſure, that ſome men cannot make ſmooth. But<note n="d" place="margin">Iſa 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>woe to him,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſay, that ſpeakes good of euill, or euill of good:</hi> and<note n="e" place="margin">Pro. 17.15.</note> 
               <hi>He that iuſtifieth the wicked, and he that condemnes the righteous, euen they both are abomination to the Lord.</hi> Proceed we now in the text: <hi>And yee are all the children of the moſt high.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a childe by generation, the expreſſe character of his Fathers perſon: ſo Chriſt the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Vnigena, the</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>onely begotten Sonne of God.</hi> There are ſonnes by creation, and ſpecially of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance in puritie; ſo are Angels called<note n="g" place="margin">Iob 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>the ſonnes of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sonnes by adoption and regeneration; <hi>ſo all the</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>faithfull:</hi> it were comfortable if ſo were alſo all Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>Children by ſemblance of maieſtie and glory, as <hi>Gods liuely</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.7.</note> 
               <hi>images in authoritie:</hi> ſo Magiſtrates and whomſoeuer God hath inueſted in the glory of ruling power.</p>
            <p>Are they all in this ſenſe ſons of the moſt high? What ſay wee to the caſe of impietie? Suppoſe them impious, ſaid<note n="*" place="margin">Quaeſtion. Armenic. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Amarcanus.</hi> All title to do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion hath foundation in the grace of iuſtice and charitie; therefore impious men haue no lawfull dominion, but by impietie make forfeiture of their authoritie.</p>
            <p>Thus wee diſtinguiſh: Its prouidence, not grace, that diſpoſeth ciuill titles: grace, not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, that makes them comfortable. It is true in a ſenſe, impious men are all vſurpers in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they enioy: the aire they breath in, the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1080:13"/> earth they tread on, the meat they eat, the clothes they are warmed with,<note n="k" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.22.23.</note> 
               <hi>are not theirs;</hi> I meane by ſpirituall right, that can giue them comfort before God: yet haue they a title indefeiſible amongſt men, by birth-right, ſucceſſion, election, or if there bee any other courſe that prouidence hath choſen, thereby to deuolue ſuch titles vpon them. Therefore wee ſay as <hi>Auſtin</hi> truly:<note n="*" place="margin">Auguſtin. de C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>at. Dei, lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Qui dedit Mario, ipſe &amp; Caeſari;</hi> hee that gaue the Empire to <hi>Marius,</hi> gaue it alſo to <hi>Caeſar;</hi> hee that to <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> the ſame to <hi>Nero;</hi> hee that to the <hi>Veſpaſians</hi> the father and ſonne, thoſe ſweete Emperours, the ſame to that moſt cruell and bloudy <hi>Domitian.</hi> And in a word, hee that to <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Chriſtian, the ſame to <hi>Iulian</hi> the Reuolt.<note n="l" place="margin">1. Tim 2.</note> 
               <hi>Pray for Kings,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> yea though they were ſuch as<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>gentilitèr vixerunt,</hi> ſaid <hi>Opta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>euitanus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſay we to the caſe of tyrannie? Suppoſe them tyrants; retaine they ſtill their honourable title and function?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> If by tyrannie they meane vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped regiment, perhaps its true that <hi>Albertus</hi> hath; ſubiection may bee performed, <hi>quoad ſuſtinentiam;</hi> needes not bee performed <hi>quoad obedi ntiam:</hi> our patience may beare their tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie; our conſcience ſeemes not bound to yeeld them obedience. If by tyrannie they vnderſtand ordinate power degenerating into crueltie by abuſe, howſoeuer Papiſts and ſome other Diuines giue libertie with cautions to throw off the yoke, yet <hi>vetera vera:</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">1. Sam. 26.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord ſhall ſmite him, or his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1080:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> day ſhall come, or he ſhall deſcend into battell and periſh. But God forbid that I ſhould ſtretch forth mine hand againſt the Lords anointed,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> of <hi>Saul,</hi> a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant by abuſe of power, though not by vſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Their vnction makes them ſacred: the hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full touch of their perſons makes the ſubiect ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious. They are <hi>flagella Domini,</hi> as is ſaid of <hi>Aſhur,</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Iſa. 10.5. Verſ. 12.</note> 
               <hi>rods</hi> to chaſten the ſecuritie and diſobedience of his people: yet ſo his rods, that the Lord onely hath authoritie to caſt them into the fire.</p>
            <p>What thinke wee of the ſtate of incorrigible hereſie, attended with excommunication? Po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſh diuinitie is knowne: the ſubiect (they ſay) is abſolued from his allegeance.</p>
            <p>I meane not to enter the queſtion, whether Kings be ſubiect to that cenſure: its probably diſputed both wayes. Yeeld that <hi>Ambroſe</hi> did iuſtly with <hi>Theodoſius</hi> in that<note n="*" place="margin">Theodoret. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. Eccleſiaſt. lib. <hi>5</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> abſtention; for I profeſſe I am yet to learne whether it were a compleat excommunication: but yeeld it <hi>ex abundante.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſentence of our Sauiour is direfull; <hi>Sit tibi ſicut Ethnicus:</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Mat 18.17.</note> 
               <hi>Let him be to thee as an heathen or Publican. Grauius eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine;</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>1.</hi> c p. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Its more then if a man were ſlaine with the ſword, or conſumed with fire, or caſt to wilde beaſts to be deuoured:</hi> yet is it but a <hi>tanquam,</hi> not a <hi>pluſquam.</hi> It make them as Ethnickes, not in worſe caſe. Suppoſe them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in caſe of Ethnickes being excommunicate: is not loyaltie to bee performed to Ethnicke Kings? What was the ſtate of Emperours and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1080:14"/> Kings when the Apoſtles gaue thoſe precepts of ſubiection, but heatheniſh? yet is it their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant rule,<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>Be ſubiect to the higher powers.</hi> And ſaith the Lord by <hi>Ieremy,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Ier. 29.7.</note> 
               <hi>Seeke the peace of the Land whither I haue cauſed you to bee carried captiues, and pray vnto the Lord for it.</hi> And who but he that hath ſold himſelfe to worke wickedneſſe in the ſight of God, dares teach, that excommunication makes parricide lawfull to the childe? or that children are abſolued from duty to parents lying vnder the ſentence of excommunication? Or why ſhould wee thinke it brings more detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to authoritie in the weale publike, then to that in priuate families? To ſhut vp the point: That ſpirituall ſword depriues of ſpirituall rights, that concerne the kingdome of Heauen, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priues none of his ciuill rights, which hee hath as a member of ciuill ſocietie.<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 16.19.</note> 
               <hi>The keyes are giuen to the Church, to open and ſhut the kingdome of heauen,</hi> meddle not at all with the kingdomes of the earth.</p>
            <p>I conclude it with that admonition of <hi>Salomon: My ſonne,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pro. 24 21.</note> 
               <hi>feare the Lord and the King, and meddle not</hi> on any pretence <hi>with them that are ſeditious.</hi> Are they impious? pray for their pietie? Are they ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannous? pray God for thy patience, and their inſpiring with clemencie. Preſumes any to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate? Know firſt, if any ſuch power bee giuen vnto men ouer Kings and Princes, yet is it inueſted in the perſons of their owne Paſtors. 2. If it be not regularly done, a nullitie there is in their conſcience, and ought to be in thine
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1080:14"/> eſteeme. 3. If neuer ſo ordinately, it depriues but of ſpirituall, not of ciuill titles.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing remaines, the infirmitie of your perſons: <hi>yee ſhall die as men.</hi> The origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall is as <hi>Adam,</hi> which <hi>Ierome</hi> takes properly,<note place="margin">Hieron. in locu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers appellatiuely; the ſenſe is both wayes the ſame.</p>
            <p>The ſentence ſome conceiue a comminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſome onely as a monition, the latter clauſe is no doubt a threatning; this former beſt interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a monition. It comes in, mee thinkes, as that <hi>ſtake in Pauls fleſh,</hi> after <hi>his extraordinary reuelations, leaſt he ſhould</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">2. Cor. 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>bee exalted aboue meaſure:</hi> or as the voice of the crier following the tryumphers Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot in Rome, eftſoones ringing that in the eare, <hi>memento te eſſe mortalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A meditation neceſſary for all men; moſt for them of higheſt dignity: how prone wee are to conceit in our very nature ſomething more then humane, becauſe our perſons are clad with diuine dignities, we ſee in plentifull experience. <hi>Herod</hi> in his magnificence admits the applauſe of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>The</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Acts 12.21.22.23.</note> 
               <hi>voyce of God and not of man,</hi> till hee lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by experience that the <hi>wormes ſhould eat him.</hi> That monſter of men in Rome, puffed vp with ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of victories, attempts to imitate thundering <hi>Iupiter. Seneca</hi> ſcoffeth at his pride: but ſo true it is that the Pſalmiſt hath;<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 49.20.</note> 
               <hi>Man being in honour hath no vnderſtanding,</hi> nor ſo much as remembrance of humane infirmity.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe, I ſeldome read of any that could hope for immortality vpon earth. But the abſurd
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1080:15"/> deſires of ſome I haue heard of, wiſhing, if it were poſſible, to perpetuate a miſerable life in this ſinful ſtate vpon earth; rather then to aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their ſoules vpon vncertaine hopes (as to them they ſeeme) of a better ſtate in the life to come. I maruell not at it. Its their profeſſion; <hi>this life they know, that other they know not.</hi> A ſpeech ſauouring of the little reliſh of the things of God: and euidencing their no title to the comforts of Gods kingdome. This life they know; would God they knew it, either as <hi>Apuleius,</hi> or but as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> deſcribes it.<note n="*" place="margin">Aug de verb. Dom. ſecund. Matth. ſer. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Inter caſus ambulamus: Wee walke amiddeſt a world of caſualties. Si vitrei eſſemus: Yet were our mettall but as glaſſe, leſſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wee had to feare miſhappes;</hi> but its much more fraile. <hi>Fals by miſhaps we feare for thoſe brittle veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells: but age or ſickneſſe wee feare not in reſpect of them.</hi> Man therefore more fraile them they; <hi>who beſides the many caſualties that haue continuall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in his life, lies open to infeebling by age and ſickneſſe;</hi> for ſuppoſe no caſualty betide vs: yet <hi>tempus ambulat, vitat homo ictum, numquid vitat exitum?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſorry wee ſhould haue cauſe to teach by inſtruction, that which fooles may learne by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.<note n="*" place="margin">Bernard. de conuerſ ad cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric. cap. <hi>14</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Death pit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth not pouerty, nor reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth riches; ſpares no mans birth nor qualitie, nor age, the ods is this onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etwixt old and young, Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibus in ianuis, adoleſcentibus in inſidijs eſt.</hi> My purpoſe is to be your remembrancer, no teacher of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</p>
            <p>This onely I beſeech you conſider with mee,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1080:15"/> 
               <hi>Wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oeuer eminence of dignitie God hath clothed you withall, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee hath not exempted you from condition of mortalitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Yee ſhall die like men</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Agapet. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. ad Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian Imperat.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the eminence of dignitie, yee are like vnto God; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the eſse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce of your body, of the ſame condition with meaneſt men.</hi> The principles of your conſtitution alone; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Clay we haue all the firſt father and founder of our generation;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>As well the Prince in his throne, as the beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar vnder the buſh,</hi> our <hi>genus</hi> is <hi>lutulentum;</hi> dirtie, at leaſt duſtie; and our ende reſolution into the ſame principles.<note n="y" place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> 
               <hi>It is appointed to all men once to dye.</hi> Remember the conſequent; <hi>after that comes iudgement.</hi> Thus thinke euen when ye ſit Iudges of other mens liues, ye haue not <hi>arbitrium,</hi> no not of your owne. <hi>There is</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.8.</note> 
               <hi>no man that hath power ouer the ſpirit, to retaine the ſpirit, neither hath hee power in the day of death, neither is there diſcharge in that warre.</hi> When thoughts of pride, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting iuſtice ſhall ariſe, thus thinke; <hi>My</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iſay 2.22.</note> 
               <hi>breath is in my noſtrills:</hi> What if the Lord ſhould cite mee to his tribunall, euen now when I thinke of abuſing iuſtice, a thing ſo ſacred?<note n="b" place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.3</note> 
               <hi>As the tree fals, ſo it lies;</hi> ſo as we die, ſo are wee preſented to iudgement.</p>
            <p>It is an error of mans pride, to thinke they ſhal haue eſteeme at that day, according as they were more or leſſe cladde with dignities in this life. Death ſtrippes of all dignities, and wee are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented naked to the Lords tribunall.<note n="c" place="margin">Apoc. 14.13</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man that dies in the Lord; his workes follow him;</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:1080:16"/> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 49.17.</note> 
               <hi>his pompe he leaues behinde him.</hi> Yet hearken to a courſe whereby yee may perpetuate iudiciall dignitie, and at the great day ſit on Thrones iudging the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Not dignitie, but ſanctitie makes vs Chriſts Aſſeſſours. The<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>Saints ſhall iudge the world.</hi> This ſanctitie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in your liues, in your callings, my ſoule for yours, your reſurrection ſhall bee glorious. In caſe it be neglected, heare what, not I, but the Lord by his Prophet threatneth; <hi>yee ſhall fall like one of the Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are witty and induſtrious niceties that <hi>Hierome</hi> hath,<note place="margin">Hier. ad loc. m.</note> enquiring the ſenſe of this commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. This one of the Princes hee conceiues to be the deuill, that prince of the aire, <hi>Lucifer</hi> the prince of the deuils, the prime deuil amongſt the Legions of infernall ſpirits. As <hi>Lucifer,</hi> ſo ſhall ye fall. <hi>Non poteſt Angelica dignitas mortem recipere, ſed tantùm ruinam.</hi> The deuill died not, but fell from the dignitie of his creation. Thus <hi>Hierome;</hi> with whom accord <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Theodoret.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtin. &amp; Theodoret. ad locum.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thus rather conceiue the Prophet, vpon <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis</hi> of their iniuſtice impenitently continued, to threaten the ruine of their thrones, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their perſons, by ſome ſpeciall hand of God. And the better to ſet before their eyes the horrour of their fall, and withall to preuent the ſecuritie might ariſe from their preſent greatnes, he remembers them of Gods wrath and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſtruction poured out vpon the Princes of the Nations, which the Lord had caſt out before their eyes, ſuppoſe vpon<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 83.11.</note> 
               <hi>Oreb and Zeeb, Zebah
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1080:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> and Zalmunnah,</hi> whoſe ouerthrow to like purpoſe the Prophet mentions in the next following Pſalme.</p>
            <p>The point here to be noticed is <hi>the iudgement of God againſt iniuſtice and crueltie, threatned and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified.</hi> Conſent of Scriptures for like threatnings reade at your leiſure, <hi>Mich.</hi> 3.9.11.12. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.3.4. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.27.31. Others many you may obſerue as you reade. Executions perhaps will more moue; and in this kinde ſtories abound.<note n="g" place="margin">1. Sam. 4.18</note> 
               <hi>The downfall of Eli,</hi> a deare ſeruant of God once Iudge in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for conniuence onely and fooliſh pitie,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.12.23.24.25.</note> (where bowels of nature might ſeeme, if not to diſpenſe with ſeueritie, yet to excuſe his lenitie) Scriptures haue regiſtred for our warning and terrour. For higher degrees of iniuſtice, records are plentifull: few tainted with that ſinne haue died <hi>the common death of men, or beene viſited with the common viſitation of all men.</hi> Of <hi>Pilate</hi> write<note n="*" place="margin">Eutrop. lib. <hi>7.</hi> Euſeb. Eccleſ. hiſt. li. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eutropius</hi> and <hi>Euſebius,</hi> how vnder <hi>Caius</hi> the Emperour he was miſerably tormented, and in the anguiſh of his ſoule choſe this <hi>compendium</hi> of his tortures, to be his owne deaths-man.<note n="*" place="margin">Tertullian. ad Scapulam.</note> 
               <hi>Vige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Saturninus</hi> Preſident and Iudge at <hi>Carthage,</hi> the firſt (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>) that drew ſword againſt vs, loſt his eyes. <hi>Claudius Herminianus</hi> Preſident of <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> after many cruel vexations of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſtricken with the peſtilence, was eaten vp of wormes.<note n="*" place="margin">Henrie. de Erford.</note> 
               <hi>Antiochus</hi> Preſident and Iudge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Aurelian,</hi> whileſt <hi>Agapetus</hi> the Martyr is in his torments, fals ſuddenly from the iudgement ſeat, and crying out of the burnings he felt in his bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1080:17"/> giues vp the ghoſt. Theſe you will ſay were at the higheſt point of iniuſtice, perſecuting to death Chriſt in his members. But remember, 1. that in iniuſtice as in other ſinnes, the downfall is headlong, and men once giuing reines to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in euill, know no ſtay till they come to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities. 2. Beſides, where the fact is not ſo foule in it ſelfe, circumſtances may make the iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice as damnable in vs. Theſe are examples of Gods immediate executions: there are others wherein hee hath vſed men as his inſtruments. The<note n="*" place="margin">A. Gellius Noct. Attic. lib. <hi>20.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Romane lawes of the twelue Tables ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed death for that Iudge that ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted to haue peruerted iuſtice for money: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording thereto were their executions, till ſuch time as corruption growing into great perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, they mitigated the ſeueritie, and exchanged it for baniſhment and conſiſcation of goods.<note n="*" place="margin">Tit. ff. &amp; C. ad leg. Ful. repetund.</note> 
               <hi>Cambyſes</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> hauing detected the corruption of a Iudge in his kingdome, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands him to bee put to death, his skinne to bee pluckt off, and ſpread vpon the iudgement ſeat as a carpet or hangings, his ſonne to ſit in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Throne ſo adorned, that he and al poſteritie might feare for euer to peruert iuſtice, and to deale vntruly in iudgement.</p>
            <p>My Lords, of theſe whether immediate or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate iudgements of God, thus thinke as <hi>Paul</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſeth:<note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 10 11</note> 
               <hi>They happened to them as enſamples, and are written for your warning,</hi> to make you cautionate how yee fall by example of like iniuſtice. I ſay as<note n="*" place="margin">Ambroſ. de Nibathe Iezra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elit. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> when hee cloſeth the Story of <hi>Achab</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:1080:17"/> and <hi>Iezabels</hi> fearefull end: <hi>Fuge ergo diues huiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi exitum. Sed fugies huiuſmodi exitum, ſi fuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris huiuſmodi flagitium.</hi> My Lords, tremble at ſuch ends, and be carefull to auoid them. Such ends yee ſhall auoid, if yee carefully flie from ſuch like iniuſtice. <hi>Faxit Deus. Cui gloria in ſaecula ſaeculorum. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
